[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you aren't speaking, there's thoughts and then there's this domain of speech that you haven't broken out into, you haven't started speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that seems different.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's different?
[SPEAKER_00]: The domain of speech, the domain of thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if speech and thought are fundamentally different, then that would mean that when you're speaking, there's also thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the speech isn't
[SPEAKER_00]: In place.
[SPEAKER_00]: In place of the thoughts, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how about when you're not speaking, but thinking to speak, but you're not actually uttering any sounds?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a problem with that?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, is there still some sort of assumption in the...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's still an assumption that you can enter the body with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, you know, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make the body... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Enter the will of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much like a linear, almost... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Channeling of your... of your thought into your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're basically assuming that you can take up... Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: With thoughts, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, kind of, enter the mouth, enter the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just sort of... any form of identifying it, to whatever extent, to that extent, it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But say you're not speaking, you're not saying anything, so you're practicing silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not actually saying anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind, obviously, is always thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what mind does, has thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, taking up of the mouth, of the verbal domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that done solely through speaking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can do that even while you're being silent?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's different kinds of thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking, like verbal thinking, thinking where you're kind of thinking in words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you think in words without taking up your mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems to me, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those thoughts are what they are, because of that, the way the mouth works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can then... you can start to see the difference between your thinking and your thinking that's taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how... how do you then not take up the mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let me ask you like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you take up the mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, well, fundamentally now, that you take up the mouth by assuming that you can take up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, how do you not take up the mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding that you can't take up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not losing the context of this body, of the mouth, untakeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Untakeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely beyond my... all anything I could possibly think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is true for putujana and for anarahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no speaking without taking up the mouth with your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, there is no grabbing things with your hand without taking up your hand with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But surely...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there's no walking across the room without taking up your body, without the body becoming...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you sort of take the body mentally as the way across the room.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But surely,
[SPEAKER_00]: An arahant could do... walk across the room without taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, that's what I'm trying to point out here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking up does not mean assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking up literally means bodily intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Borrowing, borrowing, using.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... verbal intention, mental intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Determining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking up means determining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can sort of use... Can we say that, like?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can sort of use... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...usage disorder after you've taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking up is intending upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you intend upon the body, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, you took it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you can walk, sit, move, whatever, extend your limbs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But speaking, it's as you said before, it's a more particular way of taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a verbal taking up of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same works for the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mental intention is the taking up of the mind, of that which is the thoughts, the ideas that have presented themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There seems to be a closer link between the body and the mind and that speech bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I would say that even...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you walk, when you move across the room, you're doing it because you want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mental intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by the way, the reason why it seems to be a closer link is because you've been practicing physical restraint for a number of years now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you taking up the body as a... out of habit, has been sort of suppressed long time ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or as the Buddha would say that a behavior has been purified well beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, now it's time to do that with the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you'll be able to do that on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, there is no problem in any domain, because that's where everything was rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is to recognize that taking up of the mouth is how you speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot speak without taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you... what you want to learn, discern, is taking up the mouth, but without assuming the identity of the verbal domain and mental domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I'm saying is, you want to recognize that taking up does not automatically mean assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you recognize that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restrain your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop speaking in the sense of don't engage in an unwholesome speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which then extends to the point of speaking without a purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unwholesome for the development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sampapalapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one of the aspects of wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speaking nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speaking... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trivial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trivial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you then speak when needed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, speaking is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is that you can't differentiate it from assuming the identity of the verbal and mental domain, merging, same, different, whatever, being confused about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, taking up of speech means taking up of the body for you, taking up of everything bodily, which means then you're subjected to everything bodily, to the hindrances, namely.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take up the whole body by taking up speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why if you practice jhānas, the... we said like mindfulness of non-speaking,
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, mindfulness of the mouth that hasn't been taken up, is what mindfulness of the body is at the time for you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just more specific type of mindfulness of the body, like being there, discerning the extent of the bodily domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you undermine your own sense of ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize there is no before or after this, or above or below.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am within it and I cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the extent of it, it doesn't matter how far it goes, how near it comes, can never enter me, as in my mind and my thoughts can never enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always these two simultaneous things present there together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, in order to understand what jhāna is, to dwell, having... having jhāna manifested, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is basically the imperturbable image of the correct extent of that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the sense of safety that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't lose anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any disturbance is within this extent that now I see fully in its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it begins by, you know, you said before, it begins by understanding the extent of the sensual domain and by overcoming
[SPEAKER_00]: Making yourself safe from the hindrances, which involves mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, and so understanding the body to the extent that... What is the absolute root, then, of safety from hindrances?
[SPEAKER_01]: Something you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, not acting out of... Sure, but more, more specifically, more accurately than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what is a necessary basis for you acting out?
[SPEAKER_00]: By body or by speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: By taking ownership of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, not necessarily... Yeah, it's ownership, of course, but you don't need to think in terms of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just taking it up because you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you learn how to not take it up, while it's there enduring on its own, means there is no basis for hindrance to basically pertain to you, turn to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the practice of jhāna, then, is practice of not taking up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, first of all, you might say, you begin by not taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, then the body becomes this more particular aspect of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but just while you were still at it, you see, you begin.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have to be careful because in the beginning, you not taking up the body is what you take up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to start thinking about the ways of not taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes time until you start discerning body on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which then manifests as... As something that can't be taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: As not being taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you're not clear about it, and it's certainly if you're acting out of your craving, you will be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I'm not taking up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not taking up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is your very extreme way of taking it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, taking up is kind of a matter of your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taking up isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taking up is basically removing the basis for taking up
[SPEAKER_01]: That then results in the experience of not taking it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the removing for basis of taking up the body is sīla.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping sīla removes the basis of taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can get to understand how to not take it up, in that negative sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I said, like, it's... you're mindful of the fact that the mouth is not speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no voice being uttered, sound being... there is no communication or expression, which means now, if there is any taking up, it's not being perpetuated by the actual acts on the verbal domain, but they're only in the attitude of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where you can see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't see it on the level of your mind as an attitude of taking up while you're talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can't see on the level of your mind the attitude of sensuality while you're engaging in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, taking up simply means determining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and practically what it means, means thinking about it, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, the only way you take up your mouth is literally by having a thought of taking it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other way that's hidden from you than the ways you take up your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as there's a possibility to take up the mouth, you've taken it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said, that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You thinking about the mouth, as in, I'm about to speak or I want to say something, that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is the significance of that thought of taking up your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for you, that thought carries the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the possibility of taking up the mouth is because...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can mentally manipulate... Well, I can speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I seem to say things and people seem to hear them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my speech is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: My voice is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me taking up the mouth is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I am taking it up because I can.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that that also means you're assuming the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you take it up without owning it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you take it up without confusing the two domains?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you take it up without identifying your thought with your speech or or interchanging and whatever else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: By practicing restraint in regard to it and then by understanding the extent of that non-speaking mouth while it's being taken up mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you actually get to stop taking it mentally because you realize that thought of the mouth cannot take up the mouth in that material sense that is being assumed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's only a direction of the mind towards speech, but you can only break into speech from its own verbal domain, not from the domain of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why having thought and ponder, one breaks into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you mean the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The determinations for speech are not mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that what you're saying?
[SPEAKER_00]: They're verbal.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a particular... there's these three domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I mean they're mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determination for speech is mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech is verbal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determination for speech is not verbal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a determination for verbal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, determination for speech is basically the thought of the mouth that takes up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, not specifically, I think, about the look of the mouth, but the mind comes down into this cavity, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you want to grab something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, your mind is in your hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, yeah, you've got... you're basically thinking about something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that has a shape of... that has some kind of bodily shape.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's assumed on some extent of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, that's already how you get to, like, how the... so to say, like, embody, as we spoke the other day, embody your personality view into the body, as if that's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you stop assuming that your mind that's in your hand, when it's about to take something you want, is actually in your hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you might say, oh, so my mind is not in my hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's another formulation between mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the mind, there is the hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the sense of space that's revealed, basically, by the body, but it's secondary already to that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you want to speak, can you speak without placing your mind, again, so to speak, in your mouth?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the necessary condition for speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whatever you're about to say, it's within that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's further of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the jhāna, you don't have that taking up of the mouth anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that embodying of those thoughts into the verbal cavity, that's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why speech has subsided.
[SPEAKER_01]: It ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: During that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, at that time, you're unable to take up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you... that's the difference between somebody who is in the first jhāna and somebody who is simply not speaking anything verbally.
[SPEAKER_01]: In his mind, through all of those verbal words and thoughts that you said, every of those, like, images and concepts that are verbalized, every verbalization
[SPEAKER_01]: is habitually taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only you're not speaking, and that's good, because then you can get to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nevertheless, that's still not like that your determination for speech has ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when those thoughts stop taking up of the of the of the verbal cavity of the mouth... Because you know that... Well, because that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was your thoughts taking up your thoughts, but for you, some of those thoughts stood for the mouth, for the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, yeah, all you have is thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but that's, that's the the funny thing, the strange thing, that we are we are skilled at manipulating the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've somehow learned to speak, to, to, to basically
[SPEAKER_00]: We've got this domain of thought and this domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two completely incompatible, separate... And domain of physical action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they're not even incompatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not even incompatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying it's compatible, incompatible, it is a form of relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relating them, comparing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're invisible to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the... if they're invisible to each other,
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems it's remarkable how we have learned how to walk, how to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's remarkable if you come from your point of view first, but your point of view is not first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's remarkable because the connection between these things escapes you, and it escapes you because it's actually fundamentally external to you, and thus inconceivable to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the only sense you... the only reason you have a sense of self and I am and logic and the mind is because these things are there beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body, the verbal domain and the mental domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to... if like... if you were to be able to understand
[SPEAKER_01]: How is thinking and pondering?
[SPEAKER_01]: How the saṅkhara of it determines the speech, for example?
[SPEAKER_01]: That would require you to step outside of yourself, to see how yourself works.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can only be conceived by somebody who has fully misconceived the sense of self, as something that comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something that can even think these theoretical things to be addressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: When the sense of how is actually secondary already to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Buddha, what he calls, sorry, by the invalid questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not invalid, because I don't want to answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Invalid, because it's simply the wrong premise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Utterly based on the wrong premise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just not worth entertaining at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, when we learn skills, we learn how to speak, we learn how to walk or ride a bike or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: All we do, all we do is just kind of fumble.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, it's like, almost like, it's almost like my questions are... And that's why it doesn't matter the extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent of your learning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's great, if it's small.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters, basically, is the sense of assumed ownership in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is gratuitous to begin with, but yes, some people invest more in it, some people less.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically speaking,
[SPEAKER_01]: Physical restraint of your senses, celibacy and so on, not breaking the precepts, is a necessary basis to outline the domain of taking up the body through erection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the verbal restraint of avoiding careless speech, malicious speech, gossip, pointless speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're being silent not because of some, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: great channeling of some energy or something, it's simply because you're outlining the domain of taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, again, a way of taking up the body, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eventually, you can also do that on the level of the mind, whereby your own thoughts and images already are taking up form.
[SPEAKER_01]: I, the body, to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's too subtle talk about it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to confuse people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through the physical restraint, you outline the domain of the body that you doubt now you're not engaging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only way to engage with the body domain is to take it up through unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to engage with the domain of speech is to take it up through unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where precepts need to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically speaking, in terms of jhāna practice, jhāna development,
[SPEAKER_01]: Physical restraint need to have been done beforehand, but now you start paying attention to your verbal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you speak, you only speak when there is a purpose to say something, to the extent that that purpose is expressed, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, then, prevents any engagement of taking up the body carelessly through your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you practice that, the less and less you assume.
[SPEAKER_01]: That ownership of the body through your mouth, through saying, through communicating, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the less you assume it, the clearer it becomes, its own nature, that it's unassumable, it's unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically the practice of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, avoid unnecessary speech, and then use that silence, basically, to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even the extent of the physical mouth that's not speaking, because that's what your body is at the time, that's where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then practice not taking that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you take it up?
[SPEAKER_01]: You take up by thinking beyond it, carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that whatever you're about to say, it's going to be within the mouth that's been taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not after, not before, not as a result of.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take... a mouth taken up is a container of your whole verbal domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, you don't take up the mouth, means you have not taken up or you cannot take up anything, the entire verbal domain, which for you at the time is the bodily domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the sense of safety that comes in the in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, the first jhāna is a result of that sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Safety from sensuality and everything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because physical and verbal, as in your mouth is a very physical thing, it's basically what your body is, for you, practically speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I referred to, that even your thoughts are a way of taking up the form, that's much subtler.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would not pertain to the same coarseness of the body in terms of sensuality and your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, if you stick with the development of the same principle, you would arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's like later on, when the noble disciple frees himself from conceit and all these other subtle things that are not anymore, sort of, expressed through the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you are not speaking, you're practicing silence, as you practice with jhāna, you have thoughts of speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't try to deny them or remove them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just now have thoughts of speaking presently and during, and try to not take up the mouth through them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let them speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without you taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, can you say, like, including them within?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not speaking up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Letting them be, basically, is another way of including them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Including them within, not... Well, including them within the silence that you are doing, for which you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot, eh... accidentally break silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only choose to be careless and then break the silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, if you practice mindfulness of the bodily postures, you cannot accidentally just find yourself standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've decided to stand up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're practicing silence, as I said, you only do so to create a container within which you want to include and allow things to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's a verbal shouting mind, doesn't matter what it is,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know that it doesn't matter how loud it gets, you are the one who chooses to speak as a result of it, and you're not doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter how much your mindfulness, recollectiveness lapses, it will never lapse for as long as you don't start speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will never completely lapse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you practice that, then, the more familiar you become with what's being included within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the verbal thing... and those things get to get to calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even your verbal thoughts will calm down, because they're not being expressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through that, you get to recognize, again, by not taking up the mouth, even on the level of your thought, not just through an act of speech, but even on the level of the thought, well, that quiets them down even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot directly tell to your thoughts, be quiet, because you just shouted it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you can think, be quiet, without you taking up the mouth with that thought, that will quiet down the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forget that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That last one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I said it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just think it, don't say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can just think it without even taking up the mouth with that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying, thinking, be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Be quiet, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought of be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind, be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you directed towards yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you then expressed through that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that direction of quiet is expressed through a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You took up the mouth and you said it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you have the thought that is taking up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's saying to yourself mentally to be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you can then refine that even further and then just have a thought of the direction of quietude without even taking up the mouth to say it, because you don't need to.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, taking up the mouth and expressing it is all secondary to the direction that the thought wanted to express, which was already a form of expression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was only like a further particularization of expression that was already within your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are used to the level of taking up the mouth or at least saying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if the person is very unrestrained, doing it physically.
[SPEAKER_00]: What were we saying before?
[SPEAKER_00]: The difference between verbal thoughts and thoughts that aren't verbal thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which is the difference between mental intention and verbal intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, verbal intention is the mental intention that also takes up the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the first jhāna, that verbal taking up has subsided.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get all the directions, all the expressions, without verbalizing it, certainly without speaking, but also without taking up the mouth, which is a basis for speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, all you need to do is think, be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in words, but in the direction of significance of being quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is container for saying be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is a container for actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: Speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is a container for some sort of physical...
[SPEAKER_01]: Writing it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shouting at others if they're not quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Blame or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to distract yourself through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you didn't get the way you wanted it to be and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're silent externally, so you get to hear your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: By hearing them, you stop basically verbalizing, you stop taking up the mouth through them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by denying them or trying to remove them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point here.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by including them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they can be without mouth taken up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mouth taken up cannot be without thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you're carelessly speaking, habitually taking up the mouth, that's what's first for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, all the thoughts are secondary, basically, to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're actually the container of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it always comes down to, like, correcting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establishing the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, essentially, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Starting with the body as the container.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the principle doesn't change.